Guide to the Lionel Trilling Papers
Rare Book and Manuscript Library Columbia University Libraries
- Series II: Correspondence, 1900-1983
  - Subseries II.2: Chronological, 1925-1976
    - 1956 August-October 19 (Box 17, Folder 4)
    - 1956 October 20-November (Box 17, Folder 5)
    - 1956 December-1957 February (Box 17, Folder 6)
    - 1957 March-April (Box 18, Folder 1)
    - 1957 May-July (Box 18, Folder 2)
    - 1957 August-October (Box 18, Folder 3)
    - 1957 November-December (Box 18, Folder 4)
    - 1958 January-February (Box 18, Folder 5)
    - 1958 March-April (Box 18, Folder 6)
    - 1958 May-June (Box 19, Folder 1)
    - 1958 July-September (Box 19, Folder 2)
    - 1958 October-November 10 (Box 19, Folder 3)
    - 1958 November 11-December (Box 19, Folder 4)
    - 1959 January-February (Box 19, Folder 5)
    - 1959 March-April (Box 19, Folder 6)
    - 1959 May-June (Box 20, Folder 1)
    - 1959 July-September (Box 20, Folder 2)
    - 1959 October-November (Box 20, Folder 3)
    - 1959 December-1960 January (Box 20, Folder 4)
    - 1960 February-April (Box 20, Folder 5)
    - 1960 May-August (Box 21, Folder 1)
    - 1960 September-November (Box 21, Folder 2)
    - 1960 December-1961 February (Box 21, Folder 3)
    - 1961 March-May (Box 21, Folder 4)
    - 1961 June-August (Box 21, Folder 5)
    - 1961 September-October (Box 22, Folder 1)
    - 1961 November-December (Box 22, Folder 2)
    - 1962 January-February (Box 22, Folder 3)
    - 1962 March-April (Box 22, Folder 4)
    - 1962 May-June (Box 22, Folder 5)
    - 1962 July-September (Box 22, Folder 6)
    - 1962 October-November (Box 23, Folder 1)
    - 1962 December-1963 January (Box 23, Folder 2)
    - 1963 February-March (Box 23, Folder 3)
    - 1963 April-May 21 (Box 23, Folder 4)
    - 1963 May 22-July (Box 23, Folder 5)
    - 1963 August-October (Box 24, Folder 1)
    - 1963 November-December (Box 24, Folder 2)
    - 1964 January-February (Box 24, Folder 3)
    - 1964 March-April (Box 24, Folder 4)
    - 1964 May-June (Box 24, Folder 5)
    - 1964 July-October (Box 25, Folder 1)
    - 1964 November (Box 25, Folder 2)
    - 1964 December-1965 January (Box 25, Folder 3)
    - 1965 February-March (Box 25, Folder 4)
    - 1965 April-May (Box 25, Folder 5)
    - 1965 June-July (Box 25, Folder 6)
    - 1965 August-October (Box 26, Folder 1)
    - 1965 November-December (Box 26, Folder 2)
    - 1966 January-February (Box 26, Folder 3)
    - 1966 March-April (Box 26, Folder 4)
    - 1966 May-June (Box 26, Folder 5)
    - 1966 July-September (Box 27, Folder 1)
    - 1966 October-November (Box 27, Folder 2)
    - 1966 December-1967 March (Box 27, Folder 3)
    - 1967 April-June (Box 27, Folder 4)
    - 1967 July-September (Box 27, Folder 5)
    - 1967 October-November 12 (Box 27, Folder 6)
    - 1967 November 14-1968 January 15 (Box 28, Folder 1)
    - 1968 January 16-February (Box 28, Folder 2)
    - 1968 March-April (Box 28, Folder 3)
    - 1968 May-July (Box 28, Folder 4)
    - 1968 August-October (Box 28, Folder 5)
    - 1968 November-1969 January (Box 28, Folder 6)
    - 1969 February-April (Box 29, Folder 1)
    - 1969 May-October (Box 29, Folder 2)
    - 1969 November-1970 February (Box 29, Folder 3)
    - 1970 March-June (Box 29, Folder 4)
    - 1970 July-October (Box 29, Folder 5)
    - 1970 November-1971 January (Box 30, Folder 1)
    - 1971 February-March (Box 30, Folder 2)
    - 1971 April-June (Box 30, Folder 3)
    - 1971 July-September (Box 30, Folder 4)
    - 1971 October-December (Box 30, Folder 5)
    - 1972 January-February (Box 30, Folder 6)
    - 1972 March-May 14 (Box 31, Folder 1)
    - 1972 May 15-July (Box 31, Folder 2)
    - 1972 August-November (Box 31, Folder 3)
    - 1972 December-1973 January (Box 31, Folder 4)
    - 1973 February-March (Box 31, Folder 5)
    - 1973 April-July (Box 31, Folder 6)
    - 1973 August-October (Box 32, Folder 1)
    - 1973 November-December (Box 32, Folder 2)
    - 1974 January-March 19 (Box 32, Folder 3)
    - 1974 March 20-April (Box 32, Folder 4)
    - 1974 May-June (Box 32, Folder 5)
    - 1974 July-September (Box 32, Folder 6)
    - 1974 October-November (Box 33, Folder 1)
    - 1974 December-1975 January (Box 33, Folder 2)
    - 1975 February-March (Box 33, Folder 3)
    - 1975 April-May (Box 33, Folder 4)
    - 1975 June-August (Box 33, Folder 5)
    - 1975 September-1976 January (Box 33, Folder 6)
- Series III: Writings, 1925-1975
  This series is the second largest in the collection and contains Lionel Trilling's extensive writings. The texts span his entire career and cover a variety of intellectual, cultural, and personal subjects. Many of the texts have accompanying annotations written by Trilling. These notations illustrate his creative process and provide insight in the way he crafted his writing. The series has been arranged into three subseries based upon the original order of the papers. The subseries are: Manuscripts and Papers, Articles, and Reviews.
  - Subseries III.1: Manuscripts and Papers, 1931-1975
    This subseries is composed of drafts of Lionel Trilling's longer writings, in the form of manuscripts, academic papers, lectures, and essays. In terms of manuscripts, there are drafts of Beyond Culture, The Liberal Imagination, and Sincerity and Authenticity. The Middle of the Journey is present in many versions that are each substantially unique. Other papers held in this subseries include lectures given at numerous institutions such as the 92nd Street YMWHA and the Aspen Film Conference, as well as acceptance speeches for various honors received, afterwards and forewords to other individual's writings, essays concerning literary and cultural events and selected book reviews. These reviews have been maintained within the subseries rather than separated into Subseries 3 in order to preserve the original order. Some of the drafts have descriptive notes written by Diana Trilling in which she compares the text in its draft form to a later published or rewritten version.
    - An Address to Jewish Students, undated (Box 34, Folder 1)
    - Afterward to The Unpossessed by Tess Slesinger, 1966 (Box 34, Folder 2)
    - "Aggression and Utopia: A Note on William Morris' News from Nowhere," undated (Box 34, Folder 3)
    - American Anthology, 1942 October (Box 34, Folder 4)
    - "The Anti-Hero," (lecture at YMHA) undated (Box 34, Folder 5)
    - "Anxious Exits: A Review of a Dance Recital," undated (Box 34, Folder 6)
    - "Art and Neurosis," 1945 (Box 34, Folder 7)
    - "Art, Will and Necessity," 1974 (Box 34, Folder 8)
    - "The Arts, The Artist, and Society," (Carnegie Tech Symposium) undated (Box 34, Folder 9)
    - Aspen Film Conference Keynote Address, 1963 August 30 (Box 34, Folder 10)
    - Autobiographical Lecture, undated (Box 34, Folder 11)
    - Beyond Culture 1965, (2 folders) (Box 34, Folder 12 to 13)
    - Beyond Culture, 1965 (Box 35, Folder 1)
    - Birthday Ode, 1946 (Box 35, Folder 2)
    - "The Changing Myth of the Jew," undated (Box 35, Folder 3)
    - Class of 1925 Speech, 1966 May 3 (Box 35, Folder 4)
    - "Clio Pops in on Mr. Guedalla," undated (Box 35, Folder 5)
    - "Coeducation: The Amalgamation of Barnard and Columbia," 1968 (Box 35, Folder 6)
    - "The Columbia Academic Community," 1968 (Box 35, Folder 7)
    - Comment on Dr. Bernard Meyer's Paper on Joseph Conrad, 1962 December 12 (Box 35, Folder 8)
    - "Contemporary American Literature in Its Relation to Ideas," 1949 (Box 35, Folder 9)
    - "Culture and the Little Magazine," 1946 (Box 35, Folder 10)
    - "Dreiser and the Liberal Mind," 1946 April (Box 35, Folder 11)
    - "Dreiser, Parrington and Reality," 1946 (Box 35, Folder 12)
    - E.M. Forster, 1964 (Box 35, Folder 13)
    - The Earthy Comedy: James Joyce, 1932 June 17 (Box 35, Folder 14)
    - Elements that Are Wanted, 1940 (Box 35, Folder 15)
    - Elliott E. Cohen, undated (Box 35, Folder 16)
    - Essays (not proofread), undated, 1952-1953 (Box 35, Folder 17)
    - The Experience of Literature
      - General, 1963-1967 (Box 35, Folder 18)
      - Drama, 1964 (Box 35, Folder 19)
      - Fiction, 1964 (Box 36, Folder 1)
      - Poetry, 1964 (Box 36, Folder 2)
    - Scott Fitzgerald, 1945 August 25 (Box 36, Folder 3)
    - "The Fair Courts of Life: James Joyce in His Letters," 1967-1974 (Box 36, Folder 4)
    - "Freud and the Crisis of Our Culture," 1955 (Box 36, Folder 5)
    - "A Gathering of Fugitives," undated, 1955-1956 (Box 36, Folder 6)
    - "General Education and the American Preparatory System," 1973 October-December (Box 36, Folder 7)
    - Harvard University Acceptance Speech, 1962 June (Box 36, Folder 8)
    - "The 'Image' of the University," 1968 (Box 36, Folder 9)
    - "The Immortality Code," 1941 (Box 36, Folder 10)
    - Introduction of Northrop Frye, 1963 November (Box 36, Folder 11)
    - "Kipling," 1943 October-1944 January (Box 36, Folder 12)
    - "Liberal Anti-Communism Revisited," 1967 May (Box 36, Folder 13)
    - The Liberal Imagination
      - Foreword to a New Issue, 1974 (Box 37, Folder 1)
      - French Translation--Manuscript, undated (Box 37, Folder 2)
      - French Translation--Notes and Revisions, undated (Box 37, Folder 3)
      - Manuscript, 1949 December, (2 folders) (Box 37, Folder 4 to 5)
      - Preface to a New Issue, undated (Box 37, Folder 6)
    - The Life and Work of Sigmund Freud (review), undated (Box 37, Folder 7)
    - Literary Criticism: An Introductory Reader--Preface, 1970 (Box 37, Folder 8)
    - Literary Criticism: An Introductory Reader--Introduction, 1970 (Box 37, Folder 9)
    - "Literature and Intellect: A Note on Contemporary American Literature," 1949 (Box 37, Folder 10)
    - "Little Dorrit," 1952 (Box 37, Folder 11)
    - "The Meaning and Making of Leadership: A Community of the Elite," undated (Box 37, Folder 12)
    - Melville Cane, 1974 (Box 37, Folder 13)
    - Memoir, 1974 (Box 37, Folder 14)
    - The Middle of the Journey
      - General, 1947 (Box 38, Folder 1)
      - Drafts
        - One through Three, 1947 (Box 38, Folder 2)
        - Four and Five, 1947 (Box 38, Folder 3)
        - Six, 1947 (Box 38, Folder 4)
        - Seven, 1947 (Box 38, Folder 5)
        - Eight--Incomplete, 1947 (Box 38, Folder 6)
        - Nine, 1947 (Box 39, Folder 1)
        - Ten, 1947, (2 folders) (Box 39, Folder 2 to 3)
        - Eleven, 1947 (Box 39, Folder 4)
        - Twelve, 1947 (Box 39, Folder 5 to 6)
        - Thirteen, 1947 (Box 40, Folder 1 to 2)
        - Introduction to Later Edition, 1976 (Box 40, Folder 3)
    - "Milton Levy," 1962 January 18 (Box 40, Folder 4)
    - "Mind in the Modern World," 1972 (Box 40, Folder 5)
    - The Modern Element in Literature, undated (Box 40, Folder 6)
    - Novel--Untitled, undated (Box 40, Folder 7)
    - "The Novelist of the Divine: A Review of Kafka's The Castle," 1965 (Box 40, Folder 8)
    - Of This Time, Of That Place --Drafts One and Two, 1940 (Box 40, Folder 9)
    - Of This Time, Of That Place --Revised Versions, undated (Box 41, Folder 1)
    - "The Oliver Twist in the Party Line," undated (Box 41, Folder 2)
    - The Opposing Self --Manuscript, 1957, (2 folders) (Box 41, Folder 3 to 4)
    - The Opposing Self --Notes and Gallery Proofs, 1957 (Box 41, Folder 5)
    - "The Other Margaret," undated (Box 41, Folder 6)
    - "Our Hawthorne," undated (Box 41, Folder 7)
    - Oxford Anthology of English Literature, 1972 (Box 41, Folder 8)
    - Palm Coast Development Seminar, 1974 December (Box 41, Folder 9)
    - "The Person of the Artist," 1957 May 20 (Box 41, Folder 10)
    - Personal Memoir, 1975 September-October (Box 42, Folder 1)
    - Perspectives U.S.A., 1952 (Box 42, Folder 2)
    - The Princess Casamassima: An Introductory Essay, 1948 (Box 42, Folder 3)
    - "The Progressive Psyche: A Review of Self-Analysis by Karen Horney," 1942 September (Box 42, Folder 4)
    - Prospectus of a Book on Matthew Arnold, 1931 (Box 42, Folder 5)
    - "Reality in America," undated (Box 42, Folder 6)
    - "A Recollection of Raymond Weaver," undated (Box 42, Folder 7)
    - "Reflections on a Lost Cause: English Literature and American Education," undated (Box 42, Folder 8)
    - Response to the Award of the Alexander Hamilton Medal, 1972 (Box 42, Folder 9)
    - Review of E.R. Wasserman's and R. Gitting's Books on Keats, 1953 (Box 42, Folder 10)
    - Richard Volney Chase, Jr., 1962 October 12 (Box 42, Folder 11)
    - Robert Warshaw, undated (Box 42, Folder 12)
    - "The Scholar's Tale," 1936 (Box 42, Folder 13)
    - "The Sense of the Past," 1942 April 8 (Box 42, Folder 14)
    - "Sex and the Science: The Kinsey Report," 1950 (Box 42, Folder 15)
    - Sherwood Anderson, undated (Box 42, Folder 16)
    - Sincerity and Authenticity
      - Outline (Box 42, Folder 18)
      - Draft One, 1970
        - Part I (Box 42, Folder 19)
        - Part II (Box 42, Folder 20)
        - Part III (Box 43, Folder 1)
        - Part IV (Box 43, Folder 2)
        - Part V (Box 43, Folder 3)
        - Part VI (Box 43, Folder 4)
      - Draft Two--Parts I through VI, 1970 (Box 43, Folder 5)
      - Final Draft--Parts I through VI, 1972 March, (2 folders) (Box 43, Folder 6 to 7)
      - Autograph Book, 1972 October (Box 54, Folder 9)
    - "The Situation of the American Intellectual at the Present Time," 1952-1953 (Box 44, Folder 1)
    - "A Speech on Robert Frost: A Cultural Episode," 1959 (Box 44, Folder 2)
    - Swift Scholarship, 1970 (Box 44, Folder 3)
    - "Tacitus Now," 1942 (Box 44, Folder 4)
    - "The Time of Life," 1944 (Box 44, Folder 5)
    - Trinity College Address, 1955 (Box 44, Folder 6)
    - "Two Analyses of Sigmund Freud"--Review, 1947 December 14 (Box 44, Folder 7)
    - Van Doren, Mark--Award Speech, 1966 February (Box 44, Folder 8)
    - Van Wyck Books: Scenes and Portraits--Review, 1953 (Box 44, Folder 9)
    - "Week of April 19," 1936 April (Box 44, Folder 10)
    - "Why We Read Jane Austen," 1975 (Box 44, Folder 11)
    - William Wordsworth, 1970-1971 (Box 44, Folder 12)
  - Subseries III.2: Articles and Essays, 1925-1974
    Subseries 2 is comprised of shorter pieces of texts, some of which have been published in journals and magazines. Few of these exist in multiple draft form. This subseries is arranged by topic and includes articles on cultural and literary events, book reviews from journals such as The New York Times Book Review, Partisan Review, and The Nation, letters to the editor, and published essays that are organized by journal title. Some notable titles include The Griffin, a journal that was published by The Readers' Subscription a group whose board members were Trilling, W.H. Auden, and Jacques Barzun, Commentary, and Menorah Journal. Of interest is a small sample of Trilling's writings that were translated into other languages or published in other countries.
    - General, 1938-1974 (Box 44, Folder 13)
    - Articles
      - Undated (Box 44, Folder 14)
      - 1930-1954 (Box 44, Folder 15)
      - 1960-1975 (Box 44, Folder 16)
    - Book Reviews
      - General, 1930-1952 (Box 44, Folder 17)
      - Kenyon Review, 1940-1948 (Box 44, Folder 18)
      - The Menorah Journal, 1929-1931 (Box 45, Folder 1)
      - The Nation, 1930-1948 (Box 45, Folder 2)
      - The New Republic, 1930-1941 (Box 45, Folder 3)
      - New York Evening Post, 1927-1929 (Box 45, Folder 4)
      - The New York Times Book Review, 1948-1957, 1974 (Box 45, Folder 5)
      - The New Yorker, 1949-1951 (Box 45, Folder 6)
      - PM's Weekly, 1941 March-June (Box 45, Folder 7)
      - Partisan Review, undated, 1937-1938, 1948 (Box 45, Folder 8)
    - Introductions to Books, 1956-1962 (Box 45, Folder 9)
    - Letters to the Editor, undated, 1933, 1945, 1966-1972 (Box 45, Folder 10)
    - Printed Essays
      - Commentary, 1949-1974 (Box 45, Folder 11)
      - Encounter, 1956-1965 (Box 45, Folder 12)
      - The Griffen, 1952-1959 (Box 45, Folder 13)
      - Horizon, 1947-1949 (Box 45, Folder 14)
      - Kenyon Review, 1940-1947 (Box 45, Folder 15)
      - Menorah Journal, 1925-1930 (Box 45, Folder 16)
      - Mid-Century, 1952-1962 (Box 45, Folder 17)
      - Morningside, undated (Box 46, Folder 1)
      - The Nation, undated, 1930, 1942-1949 (Box 46, Folder 2)
      - The New Republic, 1943-1944 (Box 46, Folder 3)
      - Partisan Review, undated, 1938-1951, 1961 (Box 46, Folder 4)
    - Transcripts--"The Best Years," 1962 (Box 46, Folder 5)
      (based on Of This Time, Of That Place )
    - Transcripts--Edmund Wilson, 1973 July (Box 46, Folder 6)
    - Translations
      - 1940-1951 (Box 46, Folder 7)
      - 1953-1954 (Box 46, Folder 8)
      - 1956-1959 (Box 47, Folder 1)
      - 1960-1974 (Box 47, Folder 2)
  - Subseries III.3: Notes, 1952-1974
    Notes used for lectures at Columbia University and other institutions are held in Subseries 3. These lecture notes are arranged by topic and cover subjects such as Russian and American Literature, Jane Austen, Rudyard Kiping, William Wordsworth and Keats. There are also a large number of notes Trilling used for his Comparative Literature Course. In addition, there are three card files holding topical notes on authors and literary works that Trilling often wrote about.
    - American Literature, undated (Box 47, Folder 3)
    - Austen, Jane, 1952-1957 (Box 47, Folder 4)
    - Byron, Lord George Gordon, 1963 (Box 47, Folder 5)
    - Comparative Literature Course
      - General, undated (Box 47, Folder 6)
      - Conrad, Joseph, 1958-1962 (Box 47, Folder 7)
      - Frazer, James G., 1959-1961 (Box 47, Folder 8)
      - Freud, Sigmund, 1959 (Box 47, Folder 9)
      - Gide, André, undated (Box 47, Folder 10)
      - Hemingway, Ernest, undated (Box 47, Folder 11)
      - Joyce, James, 1959-1966 (Box 48, Folder 1)
      - Kafka, Franz, undated (Box 48, Folder 2)
      - Lawrence, D.H., 1963-1964 (Box 48, Folder 3)
      - Mann, Thomas, 1958-1962 (Box 48, Folder 4)
      - Nietzsche, W., 1958-1963 (Box 48, Folder 5)
      - Shaw, George Bernard, 1962 November (Box 48, Folder 6)
      - Thackeray, W.M., undated (Box 48, Folder 7)
      - Yeats, William B., 1958-1963 (Box 48, Folder 8)
    - Contemporary American Literature Course, undated (Box 48, Folder 9)
    - Dickens, Charles, 1952 (Box 48, Folder 10)
    - Endymion, undated (Box 48, Folder 11)
    - Erikson, Erik, undated (Box 48, Folder 12)
    - Freud, Sigmund and Jung, Carl Gustav, undated (Box 48, Folder 13)
    - Huckleberry Finn, 1973 (Box 48, Folder 14)
    - Keats, John, undated (Box 49, Folder 1)
    - Kipling, Rudyard, 1972 (Box 49, Folder 2)
    - Middlemarch, " undated (Box 49, Folder 3)
    - Russian Literature, 1959 February (Box 49, Folder 4)
    - Sartur Resartus, undated (Box 49, Folder 5)
    - Scott, Sir Walter, undated (Box 49, Folder 6)
    - Sincerity--Oxford University Lectures, undated (Box 49, Folder 7)
    - Sincerity and Authenticity--Columbia University Seminar, undated (Box 49, Folder 8)
    - Swift, Jonathon, 1958-1969 (Box 49, Folder 9)
    - Twain, Mark: Innocents Abroad, undated (Box 49, Folder 10)
    - Wordsworth, William
      - General, 1962-1964 (Box 49, Folder 11)
      - Bibliographies, 1955-1974 (Box 49, Folder 12)
      - Lectures I through VII, undated (Box 49, Folder 13)
    - Wuthering Heights, undated (Box 49, Folder 14)
    - Card Files
      - American Authors (Box 50)
      - Arendt, Hannah: On Revolution (Box 50)
      - Austen, Jane (Box 50)
      - Bibliographical Notes (Box 50)
      - Cather, Willa (Box 50)
      - Crane, Stephen (Box 50)
      - Dreiser, Theodore (Box 50)
      - Eliot, T.S. (Box 50)
      - Freud, Sigmund (Box 50)
      - Fuller, H.B. (Box 50)
      - Huckleberry Finn (Box 50)
      - James, Henry (Box 50)
      - Karlinsky, Simon (Box 50)
      - Keats, John (Box 50)
      - Lederer, Emil (Box 50)
      - Lewes, G.H. (Box 50)
      - Robinson: The Freudian Left (Box 50)
      - Rousseau, J.J. (Box 50)
      - Sincerity and Authenticity (Box 50)
      - Walzer: Revolution of the Saints (Box 50)
      - Wharton, Edith (Box 50)
      - Wordsworth, William (Box 50)
      - Miscellaneous Authors and Subjects (Box 50)
      - Swift Scholarship (Box 50)
    - Card Files
      - Austen, Jane (Box 51)
      - Conrad, Joseph (Box 51)
      - Dostoevsky, Fyodor (Box 51)
      - Eliot, T.S. (Box 51)
      - Faulkner (Box 51)
      - Gide, A. (Box 51)
      - Joyce, James (Box 51)
      - Kafka (Box 51)
      - Keats, John (Box 51)
      - Lawrence, D.H. (Box 51)
      - Mann, T. (Box 51)
      - Nietzsche (Box 51)
      - Rousseau, J.J. (Box 51)
      - Swift, J. (Box 51)
      - Yeats, W.B. (Box 51)
      - Modern Literature: Miscellaneous (Box 51)
    - Card Files
      - Wordsworth (Box 52)
- Series IV: Professional Work, 1926-1987
  The records in Series IV document Trilling's professional career as a professor of Literature, a literary critic, and a commentator on the changing political and cultural landscape of the United States. Included in this series are accolades, such as honorary degrees, awards, and grants received as well as meeting minutes and notices from professional organizations that Trilling was a member of. Columbia University records, such as committee correspondence and reports, course syllabi and attendance lists. This series is arranged by topic.
  - General, 1946-1952, 1965 (Box 53, Folder 1)
  - Aspen Institute, 1963 August (Box 53, Folder 2)
  - Awards, 1951, 1974 (Box 53, Folder 3)
  - BBC Radio Shows, 1972-1973 (Box 53, Folder 4)
  - The Century Association, 1959, 1974-1975 (Box 53, Folder 5)
  - Columbia University
    - Administrative Records, undated, 1933, 1956, 1975 (Box 53, Folder 6)
    - Alexander Hamilton Medal, 1972 March (Box 53, Folder 7)
    - Examinations, 1952, 1966 (Box 53, Folder 8)
    - Grade Books, undated, 1960-1968 (Box 53, Folder 9)
      [Restricted until 2040]
    - Library, undated (Box 53, Folder 10)
    - Printed Material, 1926, 1939-1941, 1976 (Box 53, Folder 11)
    - Reference Letters, 1957-1975 (Box 53, Folder 12)
      [Restricted until 2037]
    - Syllabi, 1966-1974 (Box 53, Folder 13)
  - Guggenheim Foundation, 1975 (Box 53, Folder 14)
  - Interviews, undated, 1974 January (Box 53, Folder 15)
  - Honorary Degrees, 1955-1974 (Box 53, Folder 16)
  - Jefferson Lecture in the Humanities, 1972 (Box 54, Folder 1)
  - Lionel Trilling Award, 1975-1976 (Box 54, Folder 2)
  - The Mid-Century Book Society, 1951-1963 (Box 54, Folder 3)
  - Posthumous Items, 1976-1977, 1986-1987 (Box 54, Folder 4)
  - Printed Material, undated, 1947-1976 (Box 54, Folder 5)
  - Visiting Scholar, 1972-1973 (Box 54, Folder 6)
  - Writings by Others, undated, 1944-1976 (Box 54, Folder 7)
- Series V: Photographs, 1905-1963
  This small series holds photographs of Lionel Trilling, select friends, and several family members. Identified individuals include Lionel Trilling as both a youth and adult, his Uncle Hyman, his mother, Fannie Trilling, and Jacques Barzun. The majority of the family photographs were bequeathed to James Trilling and not included in the donation of this archive. For more photographs, please see the Diana Trilling Papers housed at the RBML at Columbia University.
  - Photographs, undated, 1905, 1945, 1963 (Box 54, Folder 8)
  - Oversized Photographs, undated, 1915-1920 (Mapcase 14-L-1)
- Series VI: Realia, 1905-1971
  Series VI contains personal memorabilia such as the baby shoes of Lionel Trilling and his sister, Harriet Schwartz, as well as some academic medals that he won while at High School and The Alexander Hamilton Award that he was given from Columbia University
  - Baby Shoe--Harriet Schwartz, 1910-1915 (Box 55)
  - Baby Shoes--Lionel Trilling, 1905 (Box 55)
  - Medals
    - The Alexander Hamilton Medal, 1971 (Box 55)
    - Clinton Club Short Story Contest, 1920 November (Box 55)
    - DeWitt Clinton High School, 1920 June (Box 55)